SANDY HAYDEN: OK, Holocaust
documentation project,
June 15, 1983.
I'm Sandy Hayden interviewing
Mr. Rubin Pinski.
Um, Mr. Pinski, um, you were
born in a little town in P--
Poland.
Can you tell us what the
name of the town was?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, the
name of town is Zdzieciol.
SANDY HAYDEN: Zdzieciol.
RUBIN PINSKI: In Polish.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
RUBIN PINSKI: In
Russian, it was Dyatlovo.
SANDY HAYDEN: Dyatlovo.
RUBIN PINSKI: And well-known
in the Yiddish name, Zhetel.
SANDY HAYDEN: Zhetel.
So how-- how do you--
how do you refer to it?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, among
friends and among, uh, people,
call it Zhetel [INAUDIBLE].
SANDY HAYDEN: OK, so can
we call it-- can we call it
Zhetel during the interview?
I think--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, I think--
SANDY HAYDEN: A little
easier for me to say
Zhetel than Zdzieciol.
RUBIN PINSKI: OK, well,
it's a very well-known town.
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah, and
um, on the map here, it--
you explained that to me
a little earlier on that
it's, um, it has a
number of big cities--
RUBIN PINSKI: Big cities around
it, yes, which is [INAUDIBLE]..
And, uh, we are also west
of, uh, [INAUDIBLE]----
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: --about 150
kilometers between [INAUDIBLE]..
Uh, our town, Zhetel,
was, uh, city's leader.
It's also well-known city.
On the other side
towards Minsk was, uh,
city in the name of [INAUDIBLE].
SANDY HAYDEN:
Yeah, and did-- did
you used to travel
often to these cities?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, not often.
I was very young.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
RUBIN PINSKI: I was just,
uh, uh, school, uh, child.
So I didn't have a chance
to travel too much.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mm-hmm.
And how big was-- how many
people were-- were in--
in Zhetel?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, the
whole population was only
about, uh, 7,500 to 8,000.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mm-hmm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And at least
60% of them are Jews.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really?
So you-- you felt that
it was more Jewish--
you felt the Jewish community
very strongly there.
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
And was sort of Jewish
community was it?
Was it orthodox or?
RUBIN PINSKI:
Well, of all kinds.
Um, the, uh, the youth were
very-- very Zionist-minded.
There was [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
in our town.
The extreme right,
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]..
There are also
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH],,
which is socialist.
Some very few communist
youth, all kinds
of, uh, organizations.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mm-hmm.
And was your family attached
to any organization?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, my
father was religious.
SANDY HAYDEN: He
was religious, yeah.
SANDY HAYDEN: And
along [INAUDIBLE]
to [INAUDIBLE] Israel.
This is a religious
organization.
And I-- I finished
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]..
And, uh, also [? learning ?]
in [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH],,
which it was called.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mm-hmm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And, uh, then I--
when I was 13, I was
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]..
It was not far from
our town, another town
called [INAUDIBLE].
They had a [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
on the, uh,
it was called
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH] from
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH].
And I was there till--
till 1939.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mm-hmm.
So you-- you had-- you had
really a religious upbringing
then?
RUBIN PINSKI: Very
religious, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: And-- and your
early schooling was just
at in the [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
with other young Jewish boys
like you?
RUBIN PINSKI:
[INAUDIBLE] once, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
And-- and you learned
all the subjects--
arithmetic and
reading and writing.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, this we
learned because the school was
subsidized by the government.
And we had to do
it to a half a day.
And all these other--
other subjects mainly
was [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]..
SANDY HAYDEN: Mm-hmm.
So that was-- half the day was--
was-- was, um, school.
And the half-- other half
of the day was religious.
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
And did you, as a young
boy, did you enjoy that?
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, yes.
I--
SANDY HAYDEN: Oh, he did.
You just never-- he never
thought, oh, I don't really
like going.
Or it wasn't too-- it-- it
wasn't-- you didn't see other
Jewish boys who maybe had half
the afternoon free because they
weren't going to town with
[INAUDIBLE] something.
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, there was
also a Yiddish [INAUDIBLE]..
And [INAUDIBLE],, as I
said, [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]..
Hebrew only.
And, uh, the youth
used to get together,
and we had
discussions for hours,
had the discussions,
one with another.
[INAUDIBLE] religious
youth and the--
SANDY HAYDEN: Zionists, yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: The-- the
other real nice gathering
[INAUDIBLE].
SANDY HAYDEN: And--
and your father--
your father let you associate
with all the other Jewish boys,
even if they weren't religious?
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: That wasn't--
RUBIN PINSKI: It was, uh,
a habit that Saturday.
My father used to
take, uh, the, uh,
children and study
with them [INAUDIBLE]
while other children were
playing football or something
like that.
But we had to obli--
oblige to our parents and--
and, uh, and do it for
them because, uh, we
always suspected our parents.
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah, yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: So we--
Saturdays, we used to see people
study with our [INAUDIBLE]..
SANDY HAYDEN: With your father.
RUBIN PINSKI:
Father [INAUDIBLE]..
SANDY HAYDEN: And how many--
how many were in your family?
RUBIN PINSKI: Four.
SANDY HAYDEN: Four.
Can you tell-- were
you the oldest, or--
RUBIN PINSKI: No, I
was the third one.
SANDY HAYDEN: The third one.
RUBIN PINSKI: My
sister was the oldest.
I had a brother and myself,
and I had a younger sister,
which perished in the--
in 1942.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And, um, what-- what did your
father do as a profession?
RUBIN PINSKI: He used to buy
grain from the farmers, grain
and, uh, other things and sell
it in, uh, a bigger wholesale.
He used-- in other words, he
used to buy it from the farmers
to sell it in the--
in the bigger-- in
the bigger wholesale.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And so did he sell it-- did
he sell it in-- in the town,
or did he take it to
the bigger cities?
RUBIN PINSKI: No.
He sold it in the
town to someone
who used to buy from everybody.
Also, he used to deal with--
what was it called?
Mushrooms.
Dried mushrooms like--
and all kinds of--
all sorts of the-- the farmers
used to sell in the city.
SANDY HAYDEN: So he used to deal
with all sorts of produce then?
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: And your mother?
Can you--
RUBIN PINSKI: Just a housewife.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
Can you-- can you
describe your mother?
What you remember.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
Very educated and, uh,
like a Jewish mother,
used to just oblige--
do the housework and, uh,
and raise the children.
Like a real good Jewish mother.
SANDY HAYDEN: Good
Jewish mother, yeah.
And did you have
quite a bit of family,
cousins, and aunts, and uncles?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
Yes, we had.
Um, not far from our house
my-- my mother's sister
and her family,
they all perished.
And my father's family
was in another city.
It's called [INAUDIBLE]
oh, about 100 kilometers
from us towards, uh, Pinsk.
And he had a brother, and
sisters, and a mother.
As a matter of fact, it was only
once in my life in that town
where my father comes from.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: I was only
eight, nine years old.
SANDY HAYDEN: So they did--
RUBIN PINSKI: I remember it
very vaguely about that town.
SANDY HAYDEN: So you much--
really, you had
much more contact
with your mother's
side of the family.
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: And did you--
you used to spend all
holidays and celebrations?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, we used
to get together on holidays.
And sometimes in the middle
of the week, we used to--
I used to play with my
cousins like a normal--
normal way of--
SANDY HAYDEN: Of growing up.
RUBIN PINSKI: A fun
way of growing up, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: And-- the--
the other 40% of
people who lived
in the town, who were they?
Were they Poles?
RUBIN PINSKI: A lot
of them were farmers.
And some were the, uh--
the administration--
the Polish administration
like policeman--
there was a magistrate.
It's like a city hall here.
And the, uh, the
mayor was a Pole.
And the secretaries were Poles.
And, uh, there was--
there wasn't a very big
administration in our town.
But, uh, and-- and
enough Poles to--
to collect taxes and--
and look after all the, uh--
SANDY HAYDEN: Administration.
RUBIN PINSKI: Administration
of the city, yeah.
SANDY HAYDEN: So that's really
all that they did there,
and the Jews were--
the Jews were involved in all
sorts of other professions
[INAUDIBLE].
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, yeah, the Jews
were all kinds of professions.
Shoe-- shoemakers, fixing shoes,
and tailors, a lot of tailors,
and, uh, storekeepers, like
groceries and selling fabric.
That was also developed
a lot in our town,
selling leather, leather
soles and leather--
the shoes were made by hand.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
Really?
Everybody's shoes
were made by hand.
RUBIN PINSKI: But there
was only one store--
while I was going up, I
remember started butter shoes.
And one store of
butter shoes opened up,
but until then,
there was no stores,
no shoes where they made shoes.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really, yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: All made by hand.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And-- and-- um, I
suppose that there
were no Jews who were farmers
or landowners around the town.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes,
there were a few
also had some farms,
not big ones, small--
small farms.
SANDY HAYDEN: So they were
allowed to own the land, and--
RUBIN PINSKI: And they
were doing the same
as other farmers,
but not too many.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: There were in
the villages around the town,
there were quite a few
Jews in the farming,
like in the other--
peasant, non-Jews,
peasants, they also
owned a couple of hectares
of land and lived from that.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: But in
the town, there was--
SANDY HAYDEN: [INAUDIBLE]
RUBIN PINSKI: Mostly the
Jews were like professionals,
like shoemakers, and tailors.
SANDY HAYDEN: [INAUDIBLE]
RUBIN PINSKI: And a lot of
Jews were just starting--
sitting and starting
[INAUDIBLE]..
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah.
And what does-- what
were the relationships
like between the Jews and
the Poles in the town?
RUBIN PINSKI: As a matter fact,
the relationship was very good.
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah?
RUBIN PINSKI: Especially with
the white Russians in our town.
The white Russians
were very nice to us.
The Poles themselves
were anti-Semitic.
SANDY HAYDEN: They were?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: So you
experienced that right from--
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: An early age.
RUBIN PINSKI: Since Hitler
came to power in 1933, the, uh,
Poles became different.
They were already anti-Semitic.
SANDY HAYDEN: Can you--
can you remember in what
way they became different?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, in the
last years in 1937, '38,
I remember they used to come
from bigger cities, young Poles
and carrying placards
saying, don't buy from Jews
and, uh, buy from Poles only.
And the anti-Semitism
started already to grow.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And do you remember-- do you
remember talking about it
as a young boy or hearing
your father and mother
talk about it.
Were they worried
about it at all?
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, yes, we all--
we knew already what
actually from the papers,
from the Jewish papers we
used to guess from, uh,
the [INAUDIBLE],, like it was,
uh, produced in, uh, Warsaw.
We used to get these papers.
And we heard what going
on in German, what
the Germans did to the Jews.
So we were already scared.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
You were worried that that could
start happening in Poland also.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, we were
very worried and scared
in the last few years
before the war broke out.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And even though the Jews were
the majority in your town, you
still, the Poles were
still openly anti-Semitic.
They weren't scared of--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yeah.
SANDY HAYDEN: --of [INAUDIBLE].
RUBIN PINSKI: No, they were--
they were very anti-Semitic
openly, but not actually not
the local Poles, always--
SANDY HAYDEN: Oh, always
Poles that came by.
RUBIN PINSKI: Came by.
And they also planted, uh,
anti-Semitism into the Poles
in our town.
But with the white
Russians, neighbors,
we lived in very peaceful.
And they were very nice.
SANDY HAYDEN: So when-- when
did all of that start to change?
RUBIN PINSKI: The last couple
of years, uh, before the war
started.
That-- wars, and
wars, and wars always.
SANDY HAYDEN: And with--
with the- white Russians
and the Poles in the town
also or still just the people
who were passing through?
RUBIN PINSKI: The Poles.
And some-- not too
many white Russians
became already a little bit
also with a cold shoulder
toward the Jews.
They were already, uh, showing
anti-Semitic, uh, tendencies.
SANDY HAYDEN: And, um, can you--
can you describe what
happened, um, in 1939 when--
when--
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, yes, well,
when the war broke out,
when the Germans attacked
Poland, the Poles, a lot
of Polish, uh, soldiers were
running through our town
towards Russia.
They were escaping
from the Germans.
And, uh, the war broke out on
the 1st of September, 1939.
And I think it was the 17th of
September the Russians came in
from-- from Minsk,
from the other side
and occupied our town.
And we came under the Russian
government and the Russian, uh,
occupation.
SANDY HAYDEN: And
did things start
to change very
much at that time?
RUBIN PINSKI: Changed--
it changed very--
very rapidly, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: How old
were you, um, when the--
RUBIN PINSKI: In 1939?
SANDY HAYDEN: 1939.
You mind me asking you?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, I
was only 15 years old.
SANDY HAYDEN: 15 years old.
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
So you were a young-- you
were a young boy then?
RUBIN PINSKI: Very young boy.
SANDY HAYDEN: Do
you remember-- do
you remember some
of the feelings
that you had when-- when--
when the Russians occupied
your town?
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, when the
Russians came, I mean, we--
we accepted them with open arms.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
You mean rather than
have the Germans--
RUBIN PINSKI: That's right.
We knew what the
Germans did to the Jews.
And they-- they were
actually, uh, liberators.
And they behaved very
nice except some of the--
from the rich Jews
took away the--
their stores.
Anybody who had a fabric
store, other kinds of stores,
they confiscated it.
But they let the
people work for them,
and they found
jobs for everybody.
And life went on fine.
SANDY HAYDEN: But
you were hearing--
you were hearing reports of
what was going on in Germany.
Can you tell me what some of
the things that you heard in--
RUBIN PINSKI: They used to
hear only from the paper
what the Germans behaved--
did bad to the Germans
Jews, also to the, uh--
when we heard the trouble
before the Russians came in.
We knew what's going more
or less on in the paper.
But the Russians concealed
from us everything.
They didn't know what's going
on in the other half of Poland.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really,
once they occupied--
RUBIN PINSKI: Once
they occupied,
we didn't know anything, just--
they told us what they
wanted to tell us.
SANDY HAYDEN: So did--
did you feel at any time
that you and your family
would like to escape or to go
to another part of Europe?
Or did you feel
that you would just
stay their for the meantime?
RUBIN PINSKI: Even if you felt--
but we couldn't do anything--
SANDY HAYDEN: You
didn't have a chance.
RUBIN PINSKI: --because
the Russian policy was you,
uh, if you are not with
us, you are against us.
In other words, if you
want to go away, you are--
you are our enemy.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So that was dangerous
for you too.
RUBIN PINSKI: So
we couldn't even
think of escaping or
going anywhere then.
We didn't have the
money to go too.
There was no-- nowhere to go.
SANDY HAYDEN: But
when the Russians
came to occupy
[INAUDIBLE],, you must
have been at you-- at yeshiva
in the neighboring town?
Or had you come back in town.
RUBIN PINSKI: No, I came back
to our town, because the, uh,
Russians, they didn't exactly--
they didn't say you
can do it, but so--
all the religious issues
disappeared somehow.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: The,
uh, officially,
they didn't say you
cannot go to synagogue,
because the Jews went
to synagogue while, uh--
while they were in occupation.
But somehow, the Jews
alone were afraid to do it.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So-- so yeshivas closed down?
RUBIN PINSKI: There was no--
no more yeshivas at all.
And then we-- we um, had
to go to Russian schools
to learn Russian.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So that's what you did
when you went back home.
RUBIN PINSKI: That's
what I did, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: So you
were at-- at a school
with Russians and Poles.
And it was now a
mix-- a mixed school.
RUBIN PINSKI: Mixed, but
we-- we taught the subjects
that are only Russian.
We started a new
language altogether.
SANDY HAYDEN: And
how was-- how was it
going to a school
like that, because it
seems to be very different
from what you were used to?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, uh, but we--
we could learn,
because the language
itself was, uh, was a lot easier
to catch, because the white--
white Russian is
similar to Russian.
Polish is also a bit
similar in a way.
And the-- the writing
and reading was harder,
but the speaking, we
caught on very fast.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And how was it to be
in the class with, um,
with other children, with the
Russian and Polish children?
Did you get on with them,
or was there anti-Semitism?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
No, no, there was
no anti-Semitism,
because, uh, they--
they knew that uh,
the Russians in the
Russian government,
there was no
anti-Semitism at all.
Everybody is the same.
And actually, they used to, uh,
punish for anti-Semitic, uh,
the writing--
saying.
They, uh, used to--
people are afraid
to be anti-Semitic.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really?
And the Poles also then
were afraid in school
to be anti-Semitic.
RUBIN PINSKI: Well,
actually, the Poles,
the few Poles that
were in our town
disappeared, the ones that were
in the administration before.
And the-- the Polish
farmers behaved like, uh,
like they have to behave
under the Russian occupation.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So how many years was--
were you under occupation
by the Russian forces?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, from
1939, from September 1939
till the outbreak of the
war at the 22nd of June,
1941 when Hitler
attacked Russia.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So that was two years.
RUBIN PINSKI: Nearly two years.
SANDY HAYDEN: Right,
nearly two years, yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: Two years, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: And in a way, it
sounds like your life didn't
change too much in those tears.
The everyday living
didn't change too much.
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, it
did change in, uh, in uh,
the way that, from one
government to the other,
which, uh, the Russians had
started to, uh, put in us--
teach-- teach us-- teach us
their ways that you cannot be
in the, uh, dealings or any,
uh, you cannot own a store.
You can-- you can't,
uh, be for your own.
Everything has to be
for the government.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: Now what you have
to work for the government.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So it was more
Marxist or socialist.
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
They tried to teach us.
But it wasn't so easy to
absorb in the beginning.
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah, so that
was a bit difficult for--
for all of you.
RUBIN PINSKI: That's right,
but it was at least safe.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And was your father
able to continue
doing what he had been doing?
RUBIN PINSKI: No.
SANDY HAYDEN: What-- what--
what did he-- what
happened to his work then?
RUBIN PINSKI: He, uh, he
used to buy, well, not
exactly the same way as to--
before used to buy direct
from the farmers and--
and sell it.
And here he had to work
for the government.
He used to buy also
from the farmers,
but, uh, like in a
cooperative sort of.
He used to write down
everything he buys
and, uh, pay out the farmers.
He worked for the
government, in other words.
SANDY HAYDEN: And
how-- how was that?
Was that a big change for him?
RUBIN PINSKI: He got
used to it first.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
But it was-- it was all right.
RUBIN PINSKI: Before
that change, yeah.
But we got used to it.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
Did that mean that,
materially, that you
had less in your family
than you were used to?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes,
uh, a little bit less,
but it wasn't too bad.
It was enough to get by.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So food, and
clothing, and shoes,
and all that sort of thing
during the Russian occupation
wasn't-- was that-- was
not too much of a problem.
You never--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, it was
a problem, because it never
brought in anything.
They took away.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: Anything
that was produced,
they took away from our
town and sent into Russia.
But, uh, we never
brought anything.
If they did bring
something, you had
to stand in, uh, a queue
for-- for hours to get it.
But we didn't complain.
It was-- they let us live.
That was-- that was
the main good thing
about the Russian occupation.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So you were just hoping that
that would continue right
until--
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: But then in 1941--
RUBIN PINSKI: 1941, when Hitler
attacked, uh, Russia, our city
was taken by the
Germans officially
until the 8th of June, 1941.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: That
was eight days later.
And in the eight
days, the, uh, there
were some battles close to our
town with the, uh, the, uh,
Russians who were running
away with the Germans who
were coming as parachutists.
The-- actually
they didn't take--
the Germans didn't occupy
our town as a full army.
But, uh, the, uh, they
parachuted behind the town
and attacked all the, uh,
running away trucks and, uh,
and tanks from the Russian.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So there was--
RUBIN PINSKI: Eight days.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really, so there
was fighting around your town
for-- for eight days.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yeah, so
fighting about eight days.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
And what was it like
during those eight days.
RUBIN PINSKI: Well,
it was very bad.
The, uh, the Jews,
uh, not only do
the whole population couldn't
get out of the houses, hiding
in the houses.
And they did get out
the, uh, the planes
shooting over the head,
the German planes.
In other words, uh,
most people were hiding.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And you must-- do you rem--
I mean, you must have been
very frightened about it.
RUBIN PINSKI: Very
frightened, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: Do you
remember the feeling?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes,
yes, I remember.
I used to hide even
in the basement.
SANDY HAYDEN: With
your whole family?
RUBIN PINSKI: The whole family
for days till-- till the, uh,
shooting got a little
bit, uh, eased.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And during those
eight days, do you--
I mean, were you
worried about what
was going to happen now
that the Russians had left?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well,
the uh, we knew
that it's not so good that
the Germans occupied the, uh,
living will be, uh,
bad [INAUDIBLE]..
We knew what to expect.
SANDY HAYDEN: You did know?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: Was this--
how hard-- how-- how did
you know this information,
because you--
RUBIN PINSKI: Well,
we knew what they do--
they did in Germany
or in Poland.
So we knew what to expect.
And so it happened.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
Can you-- can you
tell us what happened
from the time the
Germans occupied?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
The German soldiers,
they came in the town.
They-- they were very careful
walking by houses singularly.
They, uh, first
came in without--
without, uh, cars, or tanks,
or just occupied the city.
And, uh, immediately,
they started,
um, they started to
ask the, uh, some
of the, uh, Polish or white--
or the-- or the
non-Jewish population
where are-- where the Jews are.
And they asked for food from
the Jews and asked for bicycles.
SANDY HAYDEN: And you
gave it all to them?
RUBIN PINSKI: Everything.
SANDY HAYDEN: They had to, yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: They
had no choice.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And they had--
right away, the Germans
had some of the, uh,
of the town's inhabitants.
Some of them where they
with them, helping them,
uh, showing them the
Jewish, uh, houses.
And they went and robbed,
and beat, and uh, and--
the three days
after the, uh, they
had already with them
some, um, placards
hanging out in, uh, three
languages-- in German,
in Russian, and,
uh, and uh, Polish.
All de-- decrees against Jews.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really?
Yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: That the Jews,
uh, cannot walk on the sidewalk.
They cannot, uh,
possess, uh, fur coats.
He cannot-- they
cannot have any gold.
They have to give it
away to the Germans--
and a long list of
decrees against Jews.
So we knew right away
the trouble started.
And, uh, slowly, the Jews
started to come out of the--
of the hiding.
And-- and, uh, the, uh, Germans
gave every day new orders
to, uh, collect food and
collect clothes for them.
And then in the, uh, third
week was in July the 5th.
SANDY HAYDEN: At that
time, had they, um,
had there been any brutality?
Had there been-- had
they killed any Jews
during those three weeks?
Or had they just beaten them up?
RUBIN PINSKI: They killed--
they made like, um,
6 o'clock was curfew.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And nobody
could go-- get out
of the house at 6
o'clock in the evening.
It wasn't evening yet.
So in several cases, some
Jews walked to one house
to the other.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really?
RUBIN PINSKI: After six of
them got shot right way.
In other words,
non-Jews weren't shot.
But Jews are shot
for-- for that.
That was the-- several
Jews were shot that way.
But then on the 15th of
July, the, uh, the uh,
order to make Judenrat.
In other words, they picked
10 of the best Jews from town
and--
and ordered them
to have a Judenrat
and have a Jewish police.
And, uh, then the, uh,
the next day, the--
SANDY HAYDEN: Do you know--
you knew some of the people who
were elected to the Judenrat?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
Actually, the best, uh, the
best, uh, people from the city.
One was a lawyer called Alter
Dvoretsky was a young man.
He was very capable.
He was at the head
of the Judenrat
and, uh, several of
religious Jews [INAUDIBLE]..
SANDY HAYDEN: So they--
they were all good people.
RUBIN PINSKI: All-- a
better class of people.
As a matter of fact,
the rabbi for our town
was also included in that.
And the men on the
15h of July, it
was only two weeks
after they occup--
they came in, they,
uh, sent the police
to tell all the Jews to
come on the marketplace,
to get on the market place
from the age of 16 to 60.
Actually, they said
officially 16 to 60,
but whenever they
caught younger ones,
they also pushed
to the marketplace.
And, uh, on that--
on that, uh, marketplace,
the Gestapo came in.
They had a-- a table
and the market chairs.
And they had a
big list of people
who they called and said,
anybody will be called out
should go forward.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And that way,
they took away 120 people.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
What sort of people were they?
All men or--
RUBIN PINSKI: All men and
the better-- the better
class of people from the
city, and the-- and the
uh, the richer and, uh, more
learned, and they packed them
in talks.
SANDY HAYDEN: How
do you-- how do
you think they got that list?
Who gave them the list?
RUBIN PINSKI: The, uh, the
list was helped by the, uh,
local, by local
collaborators to the Germans.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
Who knew the people in
the-- the Jewish people.
RUBIN PINSKI: They
knew everybody.
As a matter of fact,
in [INAUDIBLE],,
in the Hebrew school,
there was a janitor,
and he could speak Yiddish
just as good as any Jew.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And he was
right away with the Germans
and gave out all the Jews
who were, uh, known in the--
in the town .
And, uh, they took--
they said they
are going to take this, uh, 120
people to work in Nowogrodek.
Nowogrodek is a bigger city than
us about 38 kilometers away.
But we found out later that they
were shot in the Nowogrodek.
SANDY HAYDEN: And when
did you find that out?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well,
we found out from--
from peasants, which saw it.
SANDY HAYDEN: So that was
the first really bad atrocity
that--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
That was only two weeks
after they entered our town.
And, uh, the kids saw all
kinds of, uh, every day they
demanded from us something
else, the Germans.
The, uh, or-- we organized
work like there was, uh,
a highway the Russians
started and didn't finish.
So they, uh, took
men who could-- well,
they were a little stronger
to work on that highway.
And I was also, uh,
working on that highway.
SANDY HAYDEN: Because
then you were a young man.
You were 16, 17.
RUBIN PINSKI: I was
young and strong, and--
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: And
I wanted to leave,
and they gave out
[SPEAKING GERMAN]..
[SPEAKING GERMAN] means
some kind of a document.
There was-- it went
by the column more
the people who were
stronger hard workers had
a red [SPEAKING GERMAN].
Some had green
[SPEAKING GERMAN]..
And, uh, the people--
the Jews were very,
uh, wanted very
much to get [SPEAKING GERMAN].
So--
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So you had-- you had a red one?
RUBIN PINSKI: I have a good
[SPEAKING GERMAN],, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: You
had a good one.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: How were you
chosen to-- to go and work?
RUBIN PINSKI: I,
uh, actually, they
were asking for volunteers,
and, uh, I wanted for this job,
so I worked on the--
on the, uh, building
that highway.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And your brothers?
RUBIN PINSKI: My
brother wasn't with me.
He was, uh-- he
was already taken--
before the at-- the
Germans attacked,
he was taken to
the Russian Army.
SANDY HAYDEN: How--
who-- who took him?
Was he conscripted
to the Russian Army?
RUBIN PINSKI: No, no.
He was already of age.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh, oh, I see.
RUBIN PINSKI: He
was born in 19--
SANDY HAYDEN: So he was in--
RUBIN PINSKI: 20.
He was 18 years old,
and he was taken legally
to the Russian Army.
SANDY HAYDEN: To
the Russian Army.
Uh-huh.
So had you-- did you keep--
manage to keep correspondence
with him during that time?
RUBIN PINSKI: It wasn't very--
it was right before the war.
All we heard-- we had only one
letter from him that is going
into--
deep into Russia.
And then we were
apart for six years.
SANDY HAYDEN: Really?
So you didn't know what
had happened to you.
RUBIN PINSKI: We
found him in 1946.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So that was-- that must have
been very hard for your mother
and father.
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: It
would be really--
RUBIN PINSKI: That's right.
SANDY HAYDEN: And your sister?
And--
RUBIN PINSKI: The sister was
the whole time with me together.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And then your younger brother.
RUBIN PINSKI: No,
my younger sister.
SANDY HAYDEN: Your
younger sister, sorry.
RUBIN PINSKI: I didn't
tell [INAUDIBLE]..
She perished in, uh, in 1942
in August together the parents.
SANDY HAYDEN: So your father--
when the Germans
came, your father
stopped, um, working, and--
RUBIN PINSKI: Right.
SANDY HAYDEN: You were the
only one that was really,
um, working on the highway.
RUBIN PINSKI: I was
the only one, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: So-- what-- what--
what were you getting
paid in any way?
RUBIN PINSKI: No.
No.
SANDY HAYDEN: Did they feed you?
RUBIN PINSKI: No, they
didn't pay us anything.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: Uh, the--
the, uh, in 1941 on
November, the Germans
told us to leave our houses
and go into a ghetto.
They made a ghetto.
The Jews themselves had to
make a fence, a wired fence,
around it.
And at that time, uh, we
could only take with us
whatever we could--
SANDY HAYDEN: Carry.
RUBIN PINSKI: Carry.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
RUBIN PINSKI: And
it happened that we
had a big-- a very
big garden and used
to have enough
potatoes to put it
in a big hole covered
with earth and hide it
for the next spring.
That was done actually
normal times too.
SANDY HAYDEN: Right.
RUBIN PINSKI: So we--
all the potato that we got from,
uh, before the winter came,
we bur--
we buried it in the garden.
And, um, so in Spring
of 1942 in the ghetto,
I had that chance I--
to open that hole and--
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: --put in the
potatoes in the ghetto so we
could have--
SANDY HAYDEN: Some food?
RUBIN PINSKI: Some
food for a while.
The whole-- the whole, uh, all
the inhabitants of that house,
we shared.
We used to bring in
like, uh, hiding it in--
in a way that the Germans
shouldn't see that they
carried potatoes in this--
SANDY HAYDEN: How did
you-- how did you do that?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, we
into the night, at night,
and brought it in.
The houses that the
Germans confiscated was--
in the front of the house
was some sort of, uh--
uh, a list that,
uh, but this house
is confiscated by the Germans.
In the front, they couldn't
get in, but from the back--
SANDY HAYDEN: You could?
RUBIN PINSKI:
--you could get in.
But it didn't do anything.
A lot of Jewish houses
were occupied by--
by, uh, local, uh, non-Jews.
But some of them are still--
our house was still
empty standing there.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So you could sneak in at night.
RUBIN PINSKI: I used
to sneak in every night
and bring a little
bit of potatoes
that I could carry myself.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And that's--
that's how we could
live for a while.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm And what
were the living conditions
like in the ghetto?
RUBIN PINSKI: Very bad.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
Can you-- can you
describe it a little bit?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, they
packed in in the house,
in a little house, about 800
square feet or 900 square feet.
They packed in about 60 people,
one on top of the other.
SANDY HAYDEN: And that's how
you and your family lived--
lived with another--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: --50 people or so.
RUBIN PINSKI: In the
basement and on top on the--
under the roof, people,
one on top of the other,
and the conditions in the
ghetto was very bad, dirty,
and no food.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
And-- and lice also.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: And what--
what did the people,
the leaders of the
ghetto, of the Judenrat,
were they fair in the way they--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, they were
very fair, but they were also--
they had the same,
uh, goals we did.
They were also afraid
of-- the Germans used them
just to get their way.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And, uh, this
out-- this Alter Dvoretsky
is from the Judenrat.
He organized a partisan
group in the ghetto.
And anybody who
could be of help--
used everybody that
could be of help.
Only the young
people he mobilized.
And myself was working in the
highway, building the highway.
I had a chance to bring into
the ghetto parts, uh, weapons.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: So we used to
tie it in bundles of wood.
SANDY HAYDEN: So
they wouldn't see.
RUBIN PINSKI: To carry it in.
And, uh, I used to take
chances to bring in parts
of rifles and ammunition.
And from time to time,
the Germans used to check
everybody-- every bundle of--
SANDY HAYDEN: Wood?
RUBIN PINSKI: Of wood,
or on the person.
Anybody that was found with
something was shot right away.
SANDY HAYDEN: So you
were lucky you never--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, I was lucky.
SANDY HAYDEN: [INAUDIBLE].
It must have been
frightening each time.
RUBIN PINSKI: Oh, yes, I mean--
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah, it's a risk.
RUBIN PINSKI: I risked
with my life all the time.
SANDY HAYDEN: Yeah, yeah.
So you joined the partisan
group in the ghetto.
RUBIN PINSKI: Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
SANDY HAYDEN: 194--
1941?
RUBIN PINSKI: 1941.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
RUBIN PINSKI: We organized the--
in the basement, we used
to put together the rifles.
SANDY HAYDEN: And did you--
did you use them?
What-- what-- what--
RUBIN PINSKI: No, I didn't
have a chance to use,
and practically, nobody
had a chance, only--
only a few young
boys, uh, were, uh,
fighting against
them in the second--
not in the second time when
the Germans killed the Jews.
The Germans killed,
uh, about half
of the Jewish population
in the ghettos
they killed in 1941
till the end of April.
SANDY HAYDEN:
Yeah, I-- can you--
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes.
SANDY HAYDEN: Can you tell
me a little bit about--
RUBIN PINSKI: That
was a very bad day.
Then my parents were--
got killed killed and my sister.
Uh, it was the 30th of
April, 1941, and the Germans,
with the help [INAUDIBLE]
of the Ukrainian police,
so there were a few white
Russian police also surrounded
the ghetto.
And, uh, very early in the
morning, about 5 o'clock
in the morning, they started
to knock on the windows
and scream [SPEAKING GERMAN].
And, uh, they told
us to gather in
that, uh, it was an old cem--
Jewish cemetery
near the, uh, the
synagogues and told
us to gather there,
all the Jews should together.
And I came there.
We, uh-- they told us to
stand in families, each family
together, all the families.
So I had that red
[SPEAKING GERMAN],,
which was considered
to be a good sign.
And I had a friend who also
had a good [SPEAKING GERMAN],,
so I told him to take
my sister, saying
that this wife and I wanted
to rescue my family, my father
and mother.
I remember they started to
select the, uh, I showed him
the [SPEAKING GERMAN].
So he said, [SPEAKING GERMAN],,
to the right, which was good.
And right after, a couple
steps from this Gestapo man,
stood other Gestapo
people, looked
at the [SPEAKING GERMAN],,
and they let me go through
and apparently chased
[SPEAKING GERMAN],,
in other words--
SANDY HAYDEN: To--
to the bad line.
RUBIN PINSKI: To--
to get killed.
They said to resettle for
labor or something else,
but they took them
behind the town.
SANDY HAYDEN: And there was
nothing that you could do.
RUBIN PINSKI:
Nothing I could do.
And my sister went
with that, uh,
my friend who had a good
[SPEAKING GERMAN] too,
and she was, uh, rescued.
SANDY HAYDEN: Is that--
that day must be a very hard
day for you to remember.
RUBIN PINSKI: A
very bad day, yeah.
They killed half of the
Jewish population in one day,
and then they
shortened the ghetto.
They cut it in half.
In other words, the, uh, all
the edges around the ghetto,
and they told the Jews--
for the Jews to put an
electric fence closer inside.
And I continued to
work on that highway.
SANDY HAYDEN:
And-- and the Jews,
your family and the other
Jews, were they taken?
What happened to them?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes,
they were taken.
They were led
through the streets.
They were taken behind the
town, and forced to undress,
and the, uh, the graves
were already dug.
It was already ready,
and they shot 50 people
at a time right--
right on top of the cliff.
They were all killed.
SANDY HAYDEN: What went
through your mind then?
Did you feel like you wanted
to avenge their deaths?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes,
that's the only thing
was in my mind to avenge.
Well, I never believed
I'll stay alive.
But at least I should be
able to avenge for the--
for what they did.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
Something that-- has that
stayed-- the feeling of it
stayed with you?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes, I still--
the feeling never changed.
Well, I can't feel exactly the
same as I felt then, but I, uh,
had that feeling all the time.
SANDY HAYDEN: And-- and so
what happened after that day?
RUBIN PINSKI: Well, the, uh,
the ghetto was shortened.
The Judenrat actually
was also killed.
They told to the Judenrat.
And, uh, they kept us
alive till August--
August 6th, 1942,
and, uh, August 6th ,
1942 happened the same thing.
The-- the Germans and
the Ukrainian police
surrounded-- surrounded
the, uh, the ghetto
and chased everybody
out in the marketplace.
But, uh, at that
time, I didn't--
I didn't run anymore to the--
on the marketplace
we were hiding.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
Who-- who is we?
You?
You and your sister.
RUBIN PINSKI: I, and my
sister, and my cousin,
two cousins of mine.
We were hiding in a--
we-- we actually dug a
hiding place under the floor.
But being so close to the, uh,
ghetto gate of the [INAUDIBLE]
was the Germans where, the
other side of the ghetto, they
had their, uh, the officers.
We were afraid that close--
close-- being
close to the ghetto
would be a lot worse if
they start digging with
or searching with, uh, dogs.
So we were running--
we were running in a
place where my cousin
was working as a carpenter.
And the-- the-- it
was inside the ghetto.
You could get in from inside
and from outside the ghetto.
The, uh-- in other words,
the, uh, there was--
the back of the building
was inside the ghetto.
The front of the building
was out of the ghetto.
So we were running there
and running-- and hiding
in the basement.
There wasn't a
dark place to hide,
but a plain, little basement
and a tiny, little window.
And we got into the basement
and about 15 people there.
Some came also running
at that the place.
We are hiding there a whole day,
and through the little window,
you could see that--
the way the Germans chased
the Jews to the marketplace
and beating them.
And, uh, towards evening, at
night, we tried to get to--
we tried to get out of there,
because we knew we cannot stay
there overnight.
And, uh, somehow everybody
wants to get out first
and started to commotion
inside when the,
uh, the Germans with the
Lithuanians and the Ukrainians
were all helping the Germans,
uh, in the gathering the Jews.
They heard noise
in the building.
And they, uh, first opened
the door, and they caught us.
And, uh, my cousin
was a carpenter and I
started to beg the Germans as--
let us live.
I-- I could carpent--
I can.
So the German
answered, yeah, yeah.
Tomorrow, we will take
you to the new house.
In other words, we knew that
they were going to shoot us.
And they pushed us in
back into the basement
and put a heavy
table on top of it.
And, uh, outside they put
a post working, watching,
watching the uh, the outside
in the little window.
But to our-- to
our luck, the posts
sat down close to the
window and fell asleep.
And the, uh, the window
was too small for anybody
to get-- to crawl through.
So we-- we stretched out all
the cement around the window
and made a bigger hole, and
slowly, we took out the shoes,
and slowly we--
SANDY HAYDEN: Escaped, yeah.
RUBIN PINSKI: We, uh,
called out, and we, uh,
said that we'll--
we'll meet right in, uh, that.
A little river was
running close by,
and we said we shouldn't
walk with the streets.
We should, uh, go with the
river, which takes us out
in the outskirts of
the-- of the town.
And that way, we--
SANDY HAYDEN: So
you all escaped.
RUBIN PINSKI: Not all.
An older woman couldn't make it.
Two-- two people still, because
they found only two people
there in the--
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
in the morning.
RUBIN PINSKI: --in the
basement the next day.
They escaped, and we wandered
around for, um, for, um,
until--
until it got, uh, light.
They escaped, my sister,
and I, and my two cousins
were running together, and
they came not very far.
They ran away about 10
kilometers out of town.
And it was already light.
We couldn't walk any further,
so we were hiding a little--
the little forest was very--
it wasn't-- it was a very
dangerous place to stay.
But we crawled into a bush.
We were hiding there.
And the shepherds could--
uh, we could see the
shepherds in the morning.
And somehow, we are lucky
that nobody noticed us
the whole day.
So the next evening,
we were trying
to get food into the
forest, because the, uh,
the forest around our
town was only about,
uh, 4 to 20 kilometers away.
SANDY HAYDEN: Were you planning
then to join partisan groups?
RUBIN PINSKI: Yes,
that was the main idea,
to join the partisans.
And, uh, the next night, we
came towards the, uh, forest
where the partisans were.
But talking to a peasant,
we knocked on the door,
and eh opened the door
to us, and he said--
he gave us bad news that
the Russian partisans are--
they are anti-Semitic, and they
killed some Jewish partisans,
which was the leader,
Alter Dvoretsky.
He was killed, and he suggested
we should go into, uh,
there was a [SPEAKING GERMAN]
like a working--
uh, it was a camp, which
was about 30 kilometers
from our town, and the town
was called [INAUDIBLE]..
And, uh, there the Germans
need these people, the Jews,
to build for them an airport.
And it was a chance to stay
alive as that farmer suggested.
And we took his advice, and
we went towards that, uh,
camp, which was--
together was about 33
kilometers to make.
So to the next,
towards [INAUDIBLE],,
we went around our town
towards that, uh, camp.
And the next morning,
we came-- we came--
we finally came to that camp.
We joined a group
of Jewish workers,
and we got into that camp.
Our feet were swollen,
because we were always
walking barefoot.
SANDY HAYDEN: And hungry.
RUBIN PINSKI: And hungry.
But the conditions in that
camp was just terrible.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: It was summer.
People slept under the sky.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
RUBIN PINSKI: And, uh,
there was very little food.
And people had to carry stones
from one place to the other
to--
to, uh, build that airport.
And, uh, the, uh, we couldn't
work here, because we--
our feet were all--
SANDY HAYDEN: Was sore.
RUBIN PINSKI: --were
beaten and swollen.
So but they forced
us to go to work.
SANDY HAYDEN: Who-- were these
not Germans again or Russians?
Who?
RUBIN PINSKI: No,
the, uh, the people
who watched us were
actually Ukrainians.
And there were Jewish police.
The Germans always had this
streak to-- the-- to have
their--
their own-- their
own people to--
to do the bad job.
So the Jewish police would
chase down the Jews to work.
Actually, they had to.
They had no choice.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
So you-- you--
you are sympathetic to their
position, the Jewish police.
You don't feel any--
RUBIN PINSKI: No, they didn't
do anything that they could help
it .
A lot of them were
actually in the partisans,
were running away to
the partisans together.
But, uh, they had no choice.
They were appointed
by the Germans,
and they to do what the
Germans told them to do.
And, uh, finally by--
by being there about
three weeks, we did--
I, for example, had to--
was chased out to go to work
on the carrying the stones.
And I was looking for a way
to go back to the partisans
till I--
one day, I found--
I noticed someone who I
knew went to the forest
yet before the slaughter
of the Jews in our town.
And when I talked to
him, and we met up,
they said that he
came to pick up Jews
from this camp to the forest.
And he gave me a
[INAUDIBLE],, a map how to--
SANDY HAYDEN: To get there.
RUBIN PINSKI: Go around.
Not to go to villages or to, uh,
in other words, to be careful
not to fall into certain,
uh, certain peasants who
helped the Germans.
And, uh, and, uh,
one-- one evening,
instead of going back to the--
the ghetto, there
was also a ghetto
in that camp, sort of a
ghetto, I stayed behind a--
a hump of stones.
And, uh, we left that camp.
SANDY HAYDEN: You, and
your sister, and cousins.
RUBIN PINSKI: My sister
and my two cousins.
SANDY HAYDEN: Uh-huh.
RUBIN PINSKI: And
another two, six of us,
and we made it during
the night to the forest.
SANDY HAYDEN: Mhm.
Well, I think we finished
the first half of the tape.
So--
RUBIN PINSKI: OK.
SANDY HAYDEN: They are going
to rewind it and then--
RUBIN PINSKI: OK.
SANDY HAYDEN: --we
can start from the--
RUBIN PINSKI: OK, in
the [INAUDIBLE] forest.
SANDY HAYDEN: In a
few minutes, yeah.